Recording in progress.
Good evening, ladies and gentlemen. I
would like to call the March 23rd
meeting of the governing body to order.
Madame clerk, would you take the the
role, please?
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> here.
>> Mr. Esabel,
>> Mr. Mr. Lebornne
>> here.
>> Mr. Moody
>> Dr. Renie,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> present.
>> Mr. White,
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> here.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> present.
>> And Mayor Collins,
>> I'm present also.
Would you please join me in the pledge
of
>> allegiance
to the flag of the United States of
America and to the republic for which it
stands. One nation under God,
indivisible, with liberty and justice
for all.
Item number four, consent agenda. All
agenda items listed with the designation
of CA are considered to be routine items
by the governing body and will be
enacted by one motion. There will be no
separate discussion on these items
unless a member of the governing body so
requests and the support by two other
members is received. Any item removed
from the consent agenda will be
considered in its normal sequence on the
agenda.
>> All right. Are there any items a member
of the governing body would like to
remove from the consent agenda?
>> Hearing none, I would entertain a
motion. So moved
>> by Mr. Caggrave, seconded by Dr.
Aldridge. All those in favor of the
consent agenda, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The consent agenda is
approved.
The next item is number 10A.
Public hearing for a Bar and Grill
liquor license application filed with
the city clerk's office for Mongolian
Bar and Grill doing business as
Mongolian Bar and Grill, 1637 Stillwater
Avenue, Sweet Se Cheyenne, Wyoming.
>> All right, we'll open up a public
hearing, but before we do that, I just
like to say uh a bar and grill license
is um a special license that's limited
by population. And after if we do assign
this one, we'll still have five left.
And so at this time, I'd open it up.
Does anybody here from Mongolian Grill
or anybody want to speak to it? Don't
have to, sir, but do you want to come up
and tell us what you're doing?
>> Appreciate you.
>> I understand we might be under new
ownership. Is that correct?
>> That's correct.
>> Can you push that button and turn that
microphone on and introduce yourself?
>> My name is Robin Kad.
>> Welcome, Robin. Yeah, I bought the grill
in December. It was declining for the
last year and a half and uh we took it
over and have been fixing all the
processes that are currently in place
and then we wanted to add a bar to that
establishment uh to continue to make
everything in there as awesome as it
could be.
>> Well, we appreciate your investment in a
community. Does anybody have a question
for the applicant?
>> Robin, welcome and thank you so much.
>> Thank you.
>> Anybody else in the community?
>> [snorts]
>> Mr. Johnson, welcome.
>> Thank you, Richard Johnson, 612 McGovern
Avenue. Um, I'm going to support my
homie, so I appreciate it if you guys
would, too. Thanks,
homie. I like that.
Anybody else in the audience?
All right. Um, the purpose of the public
hearing. Oh, let's go to the governing
body. Last second. Anybody? Uh, the
purpose of the public hearing has been
met. We're going to assign this item to
the finance committee.
>> Agenda item number 11, ordinance third
reading, repealing and replacing
ordinance number 4603,
which specified the monthly storm water
runoff management system user fee in
accordance with section 13.32.050
of the municipal code of the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming.
>> All right. This is an ordinance that
would repeal our storm water field fee.
It's really in collaboration with um the
legislature. Um they have agreed to work
with us this um this interim this summer
uh to see if there's some ways that we
might be able to uh find a way forward.
Um and then at the end of that period of
time, we can either reestablish it or
hopefully have a different path forward
that would come from the legislature. Uh
at this time, I'd go out to the audience
if anybody wants to speak to this item.
Mr. Johnson.
>> Yes. Once again, Richard Johnson, 612
McGovern Avenue. Um, I'll start off by
kind of going off of what you just said.
I don't trust the legislature. And, you
know, and really watching the last two
years in regards to even uh interimm
topics, you once they even go through
their interms, it's not even guaranteed
that it's going to be heard, you know,
in front of the general session. So, I
just don't believe them. And after
watching the last few council meetings,
you know, in regards to the farm and
seeing like six of them come up here and
basically not support this, you know,
they're up there, too. And it doesn't
look like the political climate in
Wyoming is going to get any better,
especially if you bring in new people.
And then they're like, well, I'm not
familiar with it. I'm not going to
really trust the interm as what happened
in 2024 and going into 25. So, I just
don't really believe them, you know? I
think that they'll just kick the can
down the proverbial road in regards to
that. Other things that I know were
problems, you know, was the school
district. Anybody that's ever done any
research in regards to a crosswalk and
know how many corners they try to cut
with the city, you know, even for safety
issues of kids, you know, this was for
flood. I mean, really, what was the city
council supposed to be for? It was
supposed to be the health, welfare,
safety of its residents. That's exactly
why we did this ordinance to begin with,
you know. You know, so when the school
district says that they're going to sue
the city because of impervious surfaces
that they don't feel that they have the
revenues for, you know, that's a bunch
of BS. They don't have the money, but
they also are going to kill their own
clients. They're going to kill their own
kids that live in the trailer park, you
know, over here off of Crow Creek.
They're going to, you know, basically,
you know, Mayor Pando ran with his own
daughter getting killed in the flood of
85. You know, Sheridan had when we
looked at the Sheridan assessment and
I'm sorry that Wes left the city, but
when we were looking at all those things
in regards to Dry Creek along the
Sheridan corridor, you know, how many of
those corridors, Converse, Hilltop,
Mountain, all of those things needed
repaired? That was the whole discussion
is that we needed a revenue stream that
could take care of this. It wasn't as
something as simple as, you know, a rain
tax or drudging some canals to free this
up. You know, this actually came with
real purpose. And I remember the
conversations because this was a council
goal I believe from 2022 on until it
passed in 2024 that you know we worked
on this for two years. Wes went out
there and he was at you know schools,
events, anything that had any kind of
civic engagement to show that the city
was actually trying to market this as
beneficial to its residents. You know,
you look at the maps. I looked at the
maps. You know, when ALF came to me and
said, "Richard, how can you not
represent the city?" I thought you were
a man of the people. And I'm like
looking at the map of the stormwater
utility going down Bradley. And I'm like
a couple of blocks from his business.
And I'm like, just because your entire
block face is impervious surface and you
may have over $1,000 in storm water
utility fees. And I was like, so you're
telling me that all those people in
those trailer parks and everything need
to die? And then once um after that
happens and everyone says, who's to
blame? And what are we going to have a
thankful Thursday for those families? I
was like, "Oh, so we can't actually make
a commitment, you know, to actually save
people's lives, but in the hindsight, we
want to look like a hero." When I sat up
there, I actually thought to myself, I
was like, I have an RV port, I have a
roof, and I have a driveway. So, I was
like, even on my own property, I knew I
had an imper enough impervious services
that I was billing myself and I knew I
wasn't going to be sitting up there. So,
I took responsibility for myself on what
I was going to pay into this utility.
And I remember sitting up there and
actually telling, you know, everybody
that spoke against it, which wasn't a
lot because I brought up a lot of other
contentious stuff at that point. But,
you know, I told them I was like, I'm
looking out for my people not even being
elected.
So, you know, I just basically go back
to it. Once these people die, and I know
that when 2023 happened, you know, had
the amount of water that we saw in 85.
So, the saturation levels were a little
different than they were in 85. We still
have the same amount of water, but you
know, it's been what, you know, that was
85. So, 41 going on 41 years. So, you
know, when what uh excuse me, when Tom
tells us about 50year flood events,
100red-y year flood events, we're
getting on to that close 50, you know,
for another one of these events to
actually happen where we're looking at a
lot of people that are potentially going
to die just like an 85 and we're in no
better shape. Well, a little bit because
of the detention ponds and stuff like
that, but unless we actually what we did
here is, you know, tried to save our
residents and property because there's
going to be a ton of property damage
when this 50-year flood comes through
here. So, remember what we did. I know
Kathy and Mark, you know, were were not
here at the time or excuse me, sorry, I
forgot. Sorry, Scott. I forgot you died.
But um and then when Larry was here or
not here, but you know, when we all made
those decisions, you know, in December
of 2024, it was to literally save our
residents. And yeah, we all had to kick
in a little bit to do it. You know, I
was here to save my neighbors, save my
community, do what was best for it. And
I'm literally worried that the
legislature is not going to do anything
for you and you're going to be back here
in 2027 after that doing the same exact
thing looking at the exact same data
with people that are no longer with the
city that actually made very very
sizable contributions not only for the
drone work but you know the resources
that went out to the community to speak
on this. So, I literally think that
looking at two years of work that West
and Tom did on this, you know, is kind
of just stabbing the back for false
promises from the legislature.
Mr. Johnson, just a a point of fact, the
um I think if we didn't do this, the
legislature would have just abandoned or
forbid us from doing it. And so, it was
a compromise to give us some time to try
to work with them to be able to get it
done. And so, but I do appreciate you
being here and and your comments today.
>> Well, that's good because I mean, you
know how good I am at fundraising. So,
with all those people that are going to
die whenever that 50-year flood event,
I'll make a Wyoming tour to every one of
those legislators homes with the people
who passed away and we'll go say you owe
an apology. Sorry for your loss.
>> Anybody else here today to speak to this
uh ordinance before us?
Anybody?
Jennifer? None. Okay.
We'll go out to uh Mr. White to uh get a
motion, please.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve on third
and final reading and I so moved.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Moody. Comments from
members of the governing body.
>> Dr. Rainey.
>> Mr. Mayor. Thank you. Um
I do want to acknowledge the comments of
my former colleague. I mean, we did
um
when we passed this, I mean, we were
thinking about loss of life and and loss
and property damage and and I do think
it's necessary. I mean, but I want
people to know and
want to remind people that we currently
spend a million dollars a year on
drainage improvements and we continue
and we will continue to do that for the
next year.
Um,
I think that in discussions with
legislators, several of them, you know,
realize this is an issue, not only in
Cheyenne, but around the around the
state. And
and maybe some of them won't see it our
way, but some of them do, and some of
them have pledged to help us. And and um
storm water drainage is the number one
topic to be undertaken by the select
committee on water. So I think that it
is it behooves us
to try and find a solution that can
address through the legislature and try
and use those work with those members
that have promised to help us um as I
said to try and find a solution that
will help us take care of our drainage
faster than what we're able to take care
our drainage issues faster than what
we're able to do it and yet not um be
perceived as a burden to property
owners. So, um I would urge my
colleagues to go ahead and vote for this
repeal. Thank you,
>> Mr. Wolf. I see your lights on.
>> Mr. Mayor, thank you very much. Um I I
won't repeat all the comments I've made
at the committee meeting and and before
the full council. I'm opposed uh to
this. I agree with um former Councilman
Johnson. Um, I um I think we need to put
a lot more money into storm drainage and
um I'm going to see if I can pursue
something to accomplish that over the
next uh couple months. Um but um I'm a
firm no on uh approving this um
ordinance. Thank you,
>> Mr. Secret.
>> Mr. Mayor, I'm I'm opposed to this, but
I'm going to vote for it.
[clears throat] Isn't that fun? Um
I realize the um damage that we could do
at the at the state level if we don't do
this. However, I think it's incredibly
important that we address
storm water. Uh, one of the other ways
I've been I've been trying to think
about other ways we might be able to do
this and perhaps we require the school
district and the mall and the other
folks that that uh really um
fought this um to eliminate any water
leaving their property
however they want to do it. but
effective X day you can no longer
contribute to our our uh tributaries.
That's another way of doing it. And if
they can figure out a better and cheaper
way to accomplish that,
that that works for me. So I'll be
working on that as we move forward.
Thank you,
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Collins through. [clears throat]
I would have to say that I agree with my
colleague from W two that um
well I um have continuously said that um
we definitely need this uh storm water
we need a way to um remedy the storm
water system that we have and um while I
didn't agree that um
the it should not have gone before the
people for a vote I definitely believe
that we need this system and I do think
it is going to be a major loss of life
if we have another a flooding event
similar to 1985.
Um and at that point it'll be too late.
Um, so I had the opportunity to visit
with um, five of our legislators from
Laramie County at recently at a ribbon
cutting and um, I'm not real confident
that they're going to be able to follow
through. In fact, I was told that the
interim topic probably wasn't going to
really help address this at all. Um,
that we should be looking for other ways
to solve it ourselves. So, um, while I
will continue to work with my colleagues
to figure out a way to do that,
um, I I believe that while we're trying
to keep our word to the legislative
body, I don't know that that um
is something that they feel compelled to
do on their part. So, um, while it'll be
a yes vote tonight in order to keep our
word to the in a promise that was made
to the legislature,
um, I I will be working to find other
ways that we may be able to remedy this
in our community.
>> Mr. Labour.
[clears throat and cough]
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Um
before I go any further, I just want to
address the idea of our word to the
legislature.
Um,
that's kind of a
strong term to use in regard to this
type of a situation because
obviously there are many many factors
that really um [snorts] probably are
going to be difficult to address.
I would say that um
when we look at that interim study
and
If any good comes out of it, so be it.
What are we going to do in the meantime
to deal with these issues? Or are we
going to wait
until after the interim, after the next
session of the legislature?
What's plan B?
And I'm not sure that we have plan B.
And I don't think that uh when you look
back at the whole situation, obviously
um
more outreach would have been a good
idea.
Maybe we ought to do some outreach right
now
over on that stretch of dry creek
between
Ridge Road and College that is just
totally choked with vegetation.
Maybe it'd be a good idea to go and
start there and show people we're coming
along with this. We're not just waiting
on the legislature.
I think we need to show what we can do
and how we can do it and where we can do
it because either way if there was such
a [snorts]
interest on the select water committee
and they
found a way to
authorize us somehow. I mean that's
really the question is is our
authorization
is it a vote of the people is it a vote
on our [clears throat] part on a fee
okay so that gets resolved
what's the collection methodology
so again um not really much choice here
but I do want to vote no to be on the
record uh that I think that uh this is
really not going to um do what I believe
some of the members hope. Thank you,
>> Dr. Evans.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um I'm going to be
a yes on this for the reason that I mean
I can't obviously argue with Richard.
He's right. Um there's definite risks
that that we have in the community. Um,
but I also think that we have this is
one of those times where we have to
balance unfortunately with we have to
compromise. Will the legislature come
through? Probably not in all honesty.
But I think we have we have to give them
the chance to do that. And the fact that
this is a statewide problem is one of my
hopes that because it is bigger than
just us, they will look favorably on
this. And the other reason that I'm
going to vote yes on this is that we
still have the infrastructure in place,
which is part is plan B. We've got the
infrastructure in place to be able to do
this. BOPU has done all the work and
Tom's group has done all the work to um
build a fee structure. So at least we
are way further than we would be
otherwise. So that that's the comfort
that I have and even though hope is not
a plan, I guess this is one of those
hopeful plans. So um I'm going to vote
yes for this.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you. Thank
you for the public comments. Um probably
a different perspective why I'm a yes
vote. mainly uh my constituents uh they
pretty much said they were opposed to it
when it was implemented. That's why they
went to the legislaturator, not just
here in Albany County. That's why
Senator Crumb brought up the bill. And
again, we know at the legislature
interim topic. But another thing, too,
is you look at some of the uh industrial
businesses like the UP Railroad, $18,000
a month is not very businessfriendly. in
the Microsoft data center of Christensen
over $5,000 a month. Magpool $1,000 a
month. Again, we have to look at that as
well, too. So, again, we need to look
forward funding it, look at our reserves
or potentially, not obviously this year,
but long run, fifth or sixth penny.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
>> Anybody else? M
>> Jennifer,
>> Mr. Escoll, you can go ahead.
Uh,
>> Mr. mayor through you.
The way I feel about it is that our
average constituent really doesn't
understand the politics of this.
and
for them to maybe come to us someday and
after an event that takes life and look
us in the eye and say, "Why didn't you
do something when you knew this could
possibly happen is something that I
don't think I could live with." And I
know there's some unfairness when it
comes to corporate
Cheyenne on the way it was charged. Uh,
I think just on principle
I'll have to be an O.
>> Anyone else in the governing body?
>> All right. Hearing none.
>> Oh, Mr. White. Thank you. [snorts]
>> Um,
this is a really difficult u vote for me
because I am like Mr. Crave. I am
opposed to this, but I'm going to be a
yes.
Um,
it's kind of this this is like taking
medicine. It sure doesn't taste good.
Um, only this is the first time in the
10 years that I've been on council where
we've dealt with something like this and
the legislature in
six, five, six years ago allowed
communities to do this.
So, we do all the leg work.
uh
tons of staff time both in the city
engineers office and at BO BOPU
and we tried to come up with a uh the
fairest way we could we could think of
uh calculating it out.
We did do lots of public input
beforehand
and then we passed the uh the ordinance
and then after the fact the legislature
comes back because
some powerful groups file suit and say
well well we didn't we didn't mean it.
And that's really difficult, really
difficult for me to understand.
However,
I will be uh voting yes tonight and
I do hope uh the legislature follows
through with this. Am I skeptical? Yes.
Um,
but if they don't, then
I'm their constituent
and they'll be they'll be hearing from
me when I vote.
>> Thank you. Any last comments,
Madame Clerk?
>> Mayor Collins?
>> Yes.
>> Dr. Emmens? [clears throat] Yes.
>> Mr. Esabel?
>> No.
Mr. Leborn,
>> no.
>> Mr. Moody,
>> hi.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> reluctantly, yes.
>> Mr. White,
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> emphatically, no.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Sadly, yes.
>> All right. This ordinance is approved on
third and final readings with Mr.
Escobel, Llayornne, and Wolf voting no.
>> Item 12, ordinance second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located north of
West College Drive and east of South
Parsley Drive or my apologies, South
Parsley Boulevard from PUD Harmony
Valley Planned Unit development to NR3
neighborhood residential high density.
All right. This is a zone change to
support building five 24 unit apartment
buildings. Uh to add some more housing
and affordability of housing to our our
inventory. We'll go out to the audience
and see if there's any comments.
>> All right. Hearing none, Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on second reading and I so move. Second
>> seconded by Mr. Crave.
Do we have comments on the zone change
by members of the governing body?
>> Hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The ordinance is approved
on second reading. Number 13, ordinance,
second reading, amending the official
zoning map of the city of Cheyenne,
changing the zoning classification for
land located south of West Allison Road,
west of Waltershide Boulevard, and north
of Grand Harmony Boulevard from PUD
Harmony Valley planned unit development
to NR3 neighborhood residential high
density.
>> All right, this is a zone change that
will allow for more density and
affordability by allowing for some
smaller homes on smaller lots. actually
196 more cottage
cottage style lots and we'll go out to
the audience and see if anybody has any
comments on this zone change.
>> All right, hearing none. Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on second reading and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave. Comments from
members of the governing body.
>> This point information
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through this
point information through you, Mr.
Mayor. Do you can you explain to the
public what you mean by uh cod style
homes so they have a better
understanding?
>> Yeah, they're just smaller smaller
homes. They're going to be priced in the
low 300,000s which shocks me to say is
an affordable house in today's world but
it is um and lots instead of being the
78,000 square foot size lots that we
normally would have um I think they're
just under 4,000 square feet and so um
they're just smaller lots uh smaller
homes is what they're they're looking to
build here.
Anybody else in the governing body?
Hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I. I.
>> Those opposed. This ordinance is also
approved on third and final reading. And
I think that's 316 units that um this
developer will be building over the next
year.
>> Did I say third reading?
>> I apologize. Second reading.
>> Was a wishful thinking. [snorts]
Item number 14, ordinance second
reading, amending the official zoning
map of the city of Cheyenne, changing
the zoning classification for land
located north of Allison Road and west
of Walterside Boulevard from AG
agricultural to NR3 neighborhood
residential high density.
>> This property is right now in an
agricultural holding zone and they don't
have any specific development plans that
they're that they've shared with us. Um,
but it is to allow for a future housing
development. Anybody in the audience
want to speak to that
hearing? None. Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on second reading and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded again by Mr. Crave. All those
on the [clears throat] council want to
say anything about this zone change
hearing. None. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed? The ordinance is approved
on second reading.
>> Number 15, ordinance second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located
northwest of the intersection of East
29th Street and Central Avenue from MR
medium density residential to NR2
neighborhood residential medium density.
>> All right. This is an existing
development of row homes or town homes
um all under one ownership and they're
trying to split this up into individual
lots so they can be sold off
individually and that's what this zone
change would allow those to be split off
and so we'll go out to the audience to
see if anybody wants to speak to the
zone change.
>> All right, Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on second reading and I so move.
>> Second. Seconded by Mr. White.
Comments from members of the governing
body on the zone change.
All right, hearing none. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. This ordinance is also
approved on second reading.
>> Number 16, ordinance, second reading.
Vacating Frank Court and a small segment
of a previously vacated alley north of
Rock Springs Street, City of Cheyenne,
Laramie County, Wyoming. located east of
North College Drive and north of Rock
Spring Street.
>> All right, this is a vacation of an
unneeded rightaway and we're here to see
if anybody wants to talk to us from the
public.
>> Okay, hearing none. Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on second reading and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave. Comments on the
vacation from members of the governing
body?
Hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. This ordinance is also
approved on second reading.
>> Number 17, ordinance first reading
amending section 13.20.050
general prohibitions and section
13.20.070
local limits of chapter 13.20 20 water
waste treatment and disposal of the code
of the city of Cheyenne, Wyoming to
revise local discharge limits and
related provisions in compliance with
MPDES and WPDEES permit requirements.
>> We'll send this one to the public
services committee.
>> Number 18, ordinance first reading,
amending section 2.76.040,
designation of downtown development
district of chapter 2.76
downtown development authority of title
2 administration and personnel of the
municipal code of the city of Cheyenne
Wyoming to expand the downtown
development district.
>> We'll send this one to the public
services committee.
>> Number 19 ordinance first reading
appropriating money for the Reed Avenue
corridor project.
>> We'll send this one to the finance
committee. Next is item item number 24A
on page four.
Contract modification number one to
contract 8267 between the city of
Cheyenne and plan one architects for the
municipal building renovation design
project.
>> All right,
welcome Miss Neck.
>> Vicki Nichek public works. Just a quick
update on this modification. Um this
modification to the is to the municipal
building renovation design project. It
adds the council building renovation
which is the old senior center um to be
redesigned as the uh new council
building and it adds the municipal court
second floor renovation design. Um this
is really just one big project with two
separate funding sources. The original
contract was funded with $2.5 million
which was approved by the voters in 2021
six in the 2021 six penny election.
Ballot question though limits the use of
the fund specifically to the municipal
building. So we can't use this on the
municipal court renovation nor can we
use it on the um the old senior center
the new council building. We are
recommending general fund reserves to
fund this modification of $867,50.
All three buildings are really pieces of
a single project which is the renovation
of the municipal building. The addition
to the north end of the current
municipal building was downsized when
the old senior center became available
and that will be the where the council
chamber offices were going to be added
on at the north end of the building. The
municipal court second floor makes space
for employees displaced during the
municipal building renovation. Several
council members actually recommended the
use of the m municipal court during the
original contract discussion at finance
committee and I just wanted to say that
it's very important that a single entity
manage the entire project as each piece
is dependent on the timing of other
pieces. So I would be happy to answer
any questions and plan one is also
available to answer questions. Thank
you.
>> We have our public works manager here,
Dr. Alders, did you have a question?
>> I do. Thank you. Mayor Collins through
you. Um, first and foremost, I guess
are we not planning to use our city
project manager to coordinate all of
these um projects um rather than relying
up on the architect or the general
contractor to try and coordinate this?
>> Mayor, through you. Normally we would we
contract with a design uh firm who also
manages construction administration
helps with the bidding and ne
negotiating for the bid. Um they do all
of that and that is the normal process
that we go through.
>> A follow-up question may cause
>> through you. Um, I'm wondering
how do how do you
believe that this is fair and equitable
to other companies who might be wanting
to bid on a project um to do this as a
contract modification?
>> Mitch,
>> through you, Mayor. Um, this project is
really one project. the we really um
would have if all of these things had
been known at the beginning. If we knew
before we went before we came before the
city council for uh the original
contract to renovate the municipal
building. Had we known um prior to
starting this whole project that the
senior center would be the next council
chambers area and the council offices.
And if we had known that you desired the
renovation of the second floor of the
municipal court, which we did not know
until the first thing we heard about it
was at that finance committee meeting
when we were talking about this. To make
it fair, um I think
plan one would have had a huge leg up to
start with because they were on this
project at from the beginning. So to go
out to a different company and try to
bring that those companies in and try to
to manage the timing of all of these
projects. First we have to get the
council chambers done. Then we have to
get the municipal court done. Then we
can move people out of here and into
another place. So those uh to start this
building before any of that is done
doesn't make a lot of sense. Um so we
felt that it was appropriate to
do a modification to the contract.
>> Thank you.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Thank you Mr. Mayor through you. Um
thank you director. Um, is there any
urgency about doing this contract
modification?
>> Miss Nichek,
>> through you, mayor. We have already
tasked plan one to draw several drawings
of the old senior center. We've already
had a work session. They have not been
paid. We do not have a contract for
that. Although we have actually asked
them to move forward with this, we
haven't spent over the limit of the
purchasing. We would be able to pay them
and stop this service if that's what we
uh desired. Um I don't think personally
that's the right move to make, but but
it could be done.
>> U Mr. Mayor, followup.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Through you. Thank you. Um,
all of us on the council got an email
from Jamie Winters, uh, who was a local
architect, um, making some very good
points about, uh, why, uh, this should
be put out to bid and that, um, local,
uh, architectural firms and, um, all of
their associated subcontractors should
be considered. And um I just uh and on
top of that uh Mr. Winter's firm uh also
was involved in the municipal court
building. So they already have a lot of
knowledge of this. And I'm just curious
about um why we think we would get a
superior result um by just going ahead
with plan one as opposed to putting this
out for a competitive bid for these two
buildings. Miss Nimichek
>> through you mayor.
We are planning to hire a CM which would
also a construction manager at risk that
would manage all three of the projects.
Um that would we would end up with
different people and so many different
people involved in this project. It
would be difficult to manage. It would
put us behind the behind the schedule
that we currently have because the
bidding process would be another
approximately three months if we put
that proposal out today which we haven't
written. We would have to first create
that RFP, send it out, uh do the entire
process. Um this seems a reasonable a
reasonable way to move forward. We have
Mr. Winters currently working on our
Westland Road project. Um his firm did
do the municipal court. Um I I was the
project manager on that as well, but
that the court upstairs is simply an
empty shell um with some bathrooms and
the HVAC system. I'm not sure why it
would require anyone it would require
Mr. Winters or anyone else to design
that specific area. It's a square.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, my question
is, are there not parameters on when we
have to put something out for bid?
>> Miss Nimichek or
is TJ on? Can we ask TJ? That's probably
a more of a TJ question.
Good evening, Mayor. This is TJ
Bartleboard. Can you hear me? Okay,
>> TJ, we hear you well and thanks for
being here.
>> Great. Absolutely. Um, so yeah, I did
have a a conversation with Mr. Winters
about this earlier this week and I can
kind of just recap to you what I shared
with him. So, um, Wyoming statute 15113,
it technically exempts professional
services from the requirement to go out
for an RFP. However, the city uh our
purchasing policy has a more restrictive
limit of $200,000
requires an RFP. So, we did um the
original contract with plan one for the
municipal building design was put out
for RFP and came before the governing
body for approval. And so, I guess the
second phase of that would be the
contract modification process. Our city
code has um those limits for what
contract mods do and don't come before
the governing body. This contract
modification does exceed that limit. So,
it is before the governing body now for
approval or for review. So, um beyond
that, there's not really a a set limit
to cap how much a contract mod is. So,
we've exceeded what we could approve
without governing body approval. So,
we're here today for uh consideration.
Hopefully, that helps line out that and
available for any other questions.
>> TJ, the original bid that um plan one
was selected from, uh how many people
were on that bid? Do you know?
>> Uh Mayor TJ Bartle, I don't know off the
top of my head exactly, but I think
think it was at least seven or eight
firms from uh across the front range.
>> And was Mr. uh Winter's firm one of
those firms?
Uh yes, the Winters Griffith was a firm
that submitted for that uh for the
proposal for the RFP for the main
contract for the municipal building
renovation.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> I do have a followup.
>> Uh Dr. Emit's followup.
>> Thank you. Um TJ, what is considered a
contract modification? Is it scope um or
is it are there def definitions of what
constitutes a modification? because this
seems like more than just adding a
little thing on. This seems like a
significant modification. So, do our
processes define what constitutes a
modification?
>> Mr. Bartle,
>> uh, Mayor Collins, threw you to Dr.
Emmens. Uh, a contract modification can
consist of, uh, change of scope,
addition of scope, extension of time,
any number of things that would affect a
project. So, um I don't know that I
would say I our our the contract
modification language that's in city
code has a couple examples of things
where if it's only for a time extension
or things like that that those things
don't require a governing body approval,
but as the scope increases and the
dollar amount increases, those things
are required to come to the governing
body for approval. There's not really an
extensive or exclusive list of what is
or isn't allowed. Um but changes to
scope in increase of scope those things
are generally what we consider things to
be handled via contract modification.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins for you. [clears throat]
I guess I'm wondering about the urgency
of this since this is supposed to be my
understanding was this was going to be
one of our six penny ballot initiatives.
Um,
I I'm not thinking that this is probably
so urgent that we couldn't um
divide this up and go out. My
understanding from the email that I
received um this afternoon was that
there have already been plans drawn for
the second floor of the municipal
building um by the architect who worked
on the municipal court building. So, I I
guess I'm I'm just not convinced of the
urgency or and don't understand
how this would be fair to anyone else
who would want to bid to basically add
on what I see is basically an entire
project to an existing project.
All right, we're still in public comment
part of our uh our situation and u
Miss Nichek, did you have
>> Vicki Nichek public works? I would just
like to say that if we don't decide to
move forward with the senior center, we
will not be able to move forward with
the design of the municipal building at
this time.
um we can't we we don't know what we're
going to do. If we don't know what we're
going to do, then we can't move forward
either with this building or any other
building. So, just a point.
Anybody else in the audience? Mr.
Johnson,
>> Richard Johnson, 612 McGovern Avenue.
One thing, it's odd listening to Vicki
talk when it talks about m multiple
funding streams, but on your agenda it
only says general fund reserves, which
concerns me. And the reason that is is
because the design concept was approved
by the voters. But I want to I would
encourage you to wait because I believe
on this item on the six penny ballot,
this is going to be the sacrificial lamb
that you had. There's just not a lot of
interest in, you know, the governmental
campus that, you know, is being
projected by your director, you know.
So, I think you kind of are if you're
going to use these monies to improve
upon your government campus just for the
design work, you know, you in hindsight,
I think this is going to come back and
bite you because I don't see this uh
passing on six penny when you actually
come to construction.
Anybody else in the audience?
All right,
Mr. White.
Motion, please.
>> Sorry, Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of
the finance committee is to approve an
amount not to exceed $867,50
and I so move
>> second
>> seconded by Mr. Crave.
You know, there was a question asked
earlier about what the urgency is and um
I guess maybe I'm a little more
optimistic than my former colleague that
we have a chance to get this passed, but
um it's a very large project. I think we
have $22 million on the six penny sales
tax and it would be my intention to uh
if this passes to build it as quickly as
we can because of the cost of inflation.
If we wait a year or a year and a half
to start this project, it'll cost us
more than $800,000 in increased costs.
So, the thought I have is that um if we
can get the uh the senior center
building done and which is something I
think we want to do and if we can get
the second floor of the uh the
courthouse done and I know this this
council this governing body has been
saying we should be doing that for a
long time and I've been resistant
because I didn't know what what our
purpose was but now that we have a
purpose we get those done um now so then
by the time November comes and we start
the the the collection we'll be able to
start that first day and um or as soon
as we can as soon as we can get
mobilized and to do that and I think
it'll save this cost in in and increased
cost and inflation and so the thought is
to do this thing in phases to get the
the auxiliary we can't do this unless we
have a place for the governing body to
go and so we'll build the senior center
building into the new u home for the the
city council meetings these meetings and
uh we'll we'll have a place for many of
our employees to go u so we won't have
to be out renting buildings or whatever
we'll be in one of our own buildings And
so I think that's the urgency. If we
don't do this now and then we wait,
we're going to be a couple years down
the road and it'll cost us more money.
Mr. White,
m Mr. Mayor, um,
if the project is kind of rests on the
whole notion of getting the senior
center or the former senior center
completed,
that
part of the project seems to be
still
questionable.
I mean, we don't know.
We don't know if if that's a done deal
yet.
And so, and as somebody who has worked
with HUD before,
um, we we very well may not know
once the, uh, ballot comes along. So,
I understand the position that Yes.
Technically
the uh second floor um courthouse,
senior center, municipal building, they
are all connected.
But as my colleague from Ward One
pointed out there
the um email that was sent did raise
some very concerning points. And when
you look at the the additional scope
that this does add, I mean, we're
talking two different buildings in
different location. Well, one's just
across the courtyard. One is in a
different location.
So,
I don't know. I I don't know. I just
have some concerns.
Amber, if I speak out of turn, holler at
me, but uh I don't think getting the
senior building is the question. and
it's what we're going to pay for it. Um
we we've made an offer to them um
looking for a discount, but um but I
think that that's the only question,
right? It's not that can we have the
building? We can have the building. It's
just the question of how much it will
cost us. We've asked for some um Well,
go ahead, ma'am.
>> Mayor through you Amber Ash, chief of
staff. We did receive some additional
communication today um regarding that.
Um, obviously there wasn't time um
before this meeting to um brief council
on that. Um there was no way to put in
an executive session before this
meeting. Um that being said, um there's
no reason to believe that we could not
acquire the building. It's a matter of
what we're willing to pay. Um and I've
had follow-up conversations with Mr.
Hancock from CHA today as well um
regarding what that might look like
going forward based on the direction
that we received from HUD.
>> Mr. or Dr.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um,
I want to remind my colleagues that
the addition
or the consideration of buying the old
senior center and moving council office
and perhaps another office there changed
the whole complexion of the project and
it changed it in midstream. Um, as
director Neichek said earlier, our
original plans was to extend this
building north,
eat up that grass area between the
current building and the parking lot,
and that's where council offices and and
and new chambers were going to go. So,
when we decided that as a council
decided that no, we wanted to pivot and
look at buying the um buying the old
senior center and move some officer over
there. that changed the whole scope of
what plan one was working on. And to me,
it seems logical that if they were
working on council offices and chambers
before, the fact that we just said, "No,
we're going to buy another piece of
property and we're going to move council
offices and chambers over there to me
seems like it is all one package deal."
Um, it doesn't make sense to when you're
trying to coordinate
parts of parts of a project to have
different people running different parts
of the project. It seems to me it would
be much more efficient to have the same
firm doing all of it. And lastly, I
disagree with my colleagues when they
say there's no rush. There is a rush.
This is, as it been noted, this is um
one of our designated projects for the
sixth penny ballot in August. And I
think we need to have more than a
conceptual idea of what we're going to
do when it's presented to the public.
So, I don't think we can delay on this
indefinitely. Um, and lastly, Mr. Mayor,
this is our pro process. And over the
years, I've seen it I've seen people
come back and say, well,
you know, would you rebid this firetruck
because our product doesn't meet your
your specifications? And I've seen other
companies make the same argument. And I
have to say that I firmly believe that
if the shoe were on the other foot, um,
the individual that wrote us the email
would not be complaining at all and
would say, "No, this makes much more
sense to stay the course as you are."
So, um, Mr. Mayor, I don't think it
makes to sense makes any sense to delay.
I don't think it makes any sense to
split up the projects. I think we'll get
a much better result if it's coordinated
by one firm.
>> Dr.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor. So, I'm going to
uh my concern is the optics of this. I
don't have an issue with doing it. I
think it makes complete sense what we're
what we're talking about doing, Mike.
And maybe it's just too many years
working in state government where there
were so tied down on um
um you know, putting things out for bid
and all that kind of stuff. Um, I I'm
just concerned about
the optics of it. Should it go out for
bid? Does that make sense? I don't know.
I mean, I could make a case either way
for using the same um architect and not
using the same architects,
but I do worry about
how it comes across to the public that
are we giving somebody priority
um in bidding.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> thank you, Mr. Mayor. uh through you. Um
I agree with all my friends on the
council. Um
let me let me just make a couple
preferatory comments. Um first I support
exactly what you're doing, Mr. Mayor, in
terms of going forward with us and chief
of staff Ash uh and and Director
Neichek. I I'm all in favor of spending
reserves to move forward on this
building and on these two other
buildings. So, and I I think I I I agree
with you, uh, Mr. Mayor, that that it
sounds like we're likely to get the old
senior center and, um, and that, uh,
will then go forward. Um, so I don't
think we really are arguing about that.
What we're arguing about is this sort of
fundamental right of um other companies
and particularly local companies, local
professionals to participate in a
competitive bid uh situation. Um and
that's clearly what this ought to be.
This is a large contract modification.
And and let me tell you what I'm not
sold on. First of all, I'm not sold on
the urgency issue. Inflation, yes,
inflation will be with us always. Um,
the urgency is sort of self-created. Um,
we don't have anybody else telling us
that we're urgent. We've been in this
building for 50 years and uh, another
couple months is probably not going to
make much of a difference. Um, second of
all, I'm I'm not at all persuaded that
having one project architect is superior
to having a couple firms even. Um, these
are professionals. Architects like
lawyers, like all sorts of of
professionals we know work together all
the time. uh the notion that somehow
that we'll this will fall apart if we
have another firm doing another part of
the building because truly we we've got
we've got these are separate buildings.
There's no reason in the world we have
to have the same architect doing the
municipal the municipal court building
and the senior center as this building.
Timing. Yes. But any professional
company can come on and move forward
with the timing. So I don't think that's
a persuasive argument. Um what is
persuasive to me is that local
professional firms are the heart and
soul of our community. Um these are the
people who serve on our boards. They
support all the events that we go to. Um
a contract like this and I I take Mr.
winner at his at his word uh is really
significant to uh to the smaller firms u
that are uh resident in this community
and I' remind the council that I mean
we've heard from Mr. Buyers who who's in
fact asked us to give [snorts]
uh local preference consideration
uh over for these kinds of contracts. We
haven't acted on that. Um but all of
those are tied together. So, I would
urge a council to not approve this uh
contract modification, to put this out
to bid. If we can expedite the RFP
process and the bidding process, that
would be wonderful. But I I think I
think we owe it to the community and owe
it to our explanation. And to Dr. Ren's
point, we have a concept. It's not like
we we don't know what we're doing. We
absolutely know what we're doing. uh as
long as these pieces particularly the
senior center fall into place. So we
don't have any problem explaining to the
general public what in fact we're doing.
We I think would be actually better
positioned to be explained to the public
that we took a large part of this
contract and put it out to bid for the
the local firms and anybody else who
wants to bid on these two separate uh
development parts. Thank you,
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Three. Yeah,
I agree with my colleague from Ward One
and all to say what I said in the uh
finance committee. I still say is
putting the car before the horse. Thank
you, Mr. Mayor.
>> Dr. Aldridge,
>> Mayor Collins, to you. Uh I first and
foremost, I I feel badly uh that plan
one has done some work and um I am going
to be a no vote on this tonight. Um
because I agree with my colleague from
war one that um the um this needs to
these are large projects or separate
buildings. I agree with my colleague
from W 2 that this is definitely about
optics um and it's also about a fairness
issue. I I am not as
um confident that this uh ballot
initiative uh will uh be passed by the
voters and um if it is not passed then
we have uh a set of plans. We have I
can't even count the number of plans
that we've paid for in the last five
years that I've been on the council. Um
and a lot of times they don't come to
fruition. um we spent almost a half a
million dollars I believe or contracted
for a half almost a half a million
dollars on the pump house that um did
not were not utilized. So um as a matter
of fiscal responsibility and knowing
that if we
um aren't able if this doesn't pass on
the six penny ballot that and we have
the plans drawn up. My experience has
been on this council that then even when
we do come around to finding the money
to do that project, we have to have the
plans adapted to the new building codes
and modified or whatever needs to be
done as was done with the three fire
stations using a plan that had been
developed previously. Still needed to
have be up brought up to code and up to
date. So, for that reason, I'm going to
be a no vote tonight. Um I I don't think
there's the urgency. I think that um the
professionals can work it out and I
think that um there's still a lot of
things that are unknown before we invest
uh over you know threequarters of a
million dollars in plans that may not
that may just sit on a shelf
>> Mr. Secret Mr. Mayor, I'll be brief. Uh,
I'm going to support this and and I just
wanted to explain why.
As we sat here, I I was trying to put
myself in position of perhaps one of the
large new members of our community and
they needed to do an addition to their
building. I can't imagine them even
considering going to an outside firm in
the middle of a building project. It
just makes it so inconvenient and
confusing and uh I'm just not sure
private industry would ever even
consider this uh to the need uh that Mr.
White brought up. Uh I was in a meeting
recently and and I know we're
considering hiring additional inspectors
for these uh large building projects.
There's nowhere in this building to
house them. So regardless if the if the
voters approve this remodel or not, we
have to find more room. Whether that's
in the uh adjoining uh facility or the
uh municipal court, we need additional
room. Um the reason honestly that we're
looking at the uh senior center is it's
cheaper. It's cheaper than doing the
buildout into the parking lot. We're
going to get the building at a a steel
um total cost there is
um le for the building is less than this
contract mud. You can't do it any
cheaper. So that makes sense to me. The
urgency
I know how slow government is. It it
just frustrates me. If we stop now and
put this out to bid and go through all
of that process, we're talking months.
Months for everything. As director
Nimichek said, the the plans for this
building until we know exactly what
we're going to do with it, either add on
to the parking lot
or not, can't go forward. Everything
stops. It's not just the um bidding for
the two additional properties.
Everything stops here.
Um, with those things in mind, it it it
makes sense to me
uh to move forward and and I certainly
hear my colleagues. Uh, I'm concerned
about local,
but when the mayor asked TJ Bartleboard
how many companies bid on this, uh,
there were seven competitors for this
project. Uh, they had their chance. I
don't feel bad that they didn't have a
chance at this. They just don't have a
chance. Well, they might at the contract
mod. Um, but they were part of the
original bidding process. So, I'm
comfortable with with where we're going.
Thank you,
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> I'm sorry. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. I'm
sorry. I have one more question. If we
were I if we vote this down tonight,
will we come is there an option to come
back with a process to rebid these other
two parts or will we just is this going
to be done?
>> No, I believe that if if you guys vote
this down today that uh I still believe
that we we can't do this building
without those other two. We will have to
do it. It's just going to set us back a
significant period of time. Thank you,
Mr. Mayor. And then my other question
is, how much time would it push it back?
>> TJ, are you there?
>> Mayor, I'm here.
>> Um, so if we started today, um, how long
would it realistically take for you to
get an RFP out, get the RFP back, go
through the process of selecting a a
person, and go through the council
process to start uh, so they could
actually get started on work. And then
how long do you think you they would
have in order or would ask for in order
to get the work done?
>> Sure. Mayor TJ Bartlebort, purchasing
manager. Um, so I guess before we can
even go out for an RFP, I'd need
assistance from the public works
department in drafting that scope of
work for what we'd be looking for in
terms of those upgrades for those two
facilities. Um, so depending on how
quick that can happen, maybe one, two,
couple weeks to have that and then we
usually say about one month for the RFP
process. Um, depending on how long
evaluations are and how many proposals
there are, there's usually a one or two
week lead time after that. And then um
the proposal would be um provided to the
governing body for approval and
depending on how the timing of the
agenda cut off and if there's a fifth
week that can take four to six weeks. So
I would say probably I think director
Nimichek said like a 3month lag time and
I think that's pretty appropriate and
that's best case scenario. So um that's
uh kind of the RFP process once the
contract's in place to go basically from
a 0% design to 100%. I think probably 6
to9 months is a best case scenario. Um,
it could take uh just depends on the
firm and their their capabilities and um
I'm not sure what uh the depth of the
renovations are at the senior center,
but um I would say probably a half a
year is a pretty safe estimate, but
director Nichek might have a little more
insight into that being more familiar
with the project.
>> And TJ, what's your workload now? How
long would it take you to get to this
RFP?
Uh, mayor, there's always lots of stuff
in the hopper, but we can always make
things a priority and make things happen
as quick as we need to do them.
>> Okay, Miss Neichek,
>> I would just like to add one thing.
Vicki Nichek, public works. We have
already asked plan one to put together
prices. Now those prices are public.
>> Yeah,
>> they
>> No, I was going to bring that up.
>> That's a problem because now everybody
knows what planes one's prices are um
this is the price of these things is in
is counted when it comes to uh the RFP
process. So I just wanted to mention
that as well.
>> Thank you
>> Dr. R.
>> Mr. Mayor, Director Nichek just made the
point I was going to do it. To me,
by going it out for bid, one's plan,
one's bids and estimates are made
public, I think it taints the entire
process.
I think that um and you know, M Mr.
Battleboard may have an opinion on that
too since he deals with this all the
time. But again, I would say if the shoe
was on the other foot and this happened
to to the individual complaining where
their figures were put out to public and
then we said, "No, let's go out to bed."
I think they'd be insensed. So,
as it is, I think we're really getting
in opening a can of worms that maybe is
better not opened.
>> Okay. Anybody else?
>> Sir, did you
Oh, I'm sorry.
>> Okay, no problem.
>> All right, so we have a motion before us
to um approve a contract modification
um with um our architectural firm. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I
>> I
>> those opposed.
>> No.
>> Okay. May I see the hands of the nose?
Mr. Wolf, Mr. Moody, Mr. uh Lebornne,
and Dr. Aldridge. the uh
>> Kenya.
Yes.
>> Okay. The contract modification is
approved.
>> Next item is number 26A on page five.
Appointment of Andy Michaelelsson to the
public transit advisor advisory board.
>> All right. I don't get to vote on
appointments that I make, but I would
take a motion.
>> I so move.
Dr. Aldridge and Mr. Cagrave.
All those in favor of the appointment,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed, the appointment is
approved.
>> Voucher report.
>> Is there anybody in the audience or on
the governing body that would like to
speak to the vouchers?
Next item, please.
>> Revenue report.
>> Same thing. Anybody in the audience or
uh on the governing body that would like
to speak to the revenue report?
Next item, please. Announcement of a
public hearing to be held April 13, 2026
at 6 PM in city council chambers 21101
O'Neal Avenue, Cheyenne, Wyoming, and
via electronic conference meeting to
determine whether compliance of
annexation conditions requested by
Wyoming statute 15-1-402
exists for about 1,259,000
sorry 1,259.9
91 acres of land located west of
Roundtop Road and adjacent to HappyJack
Road. Other business?
>> Um, do we want to do the designation of
the official?
>> That's on consent agenda, sir.
>> Oh, you got it right. I had my finger on
top of it. All right. Other business. Is
anybody in the audience here today to
speak to us under other business?
Mr. Johnson, you have three minutes.
Jennifer, start the clock.
>> Oh, she's up.
>> I got you, brother.
>> Okay. [laughter]
So, sorry, Matt. Um, so anyways, all
right. So, under other business, so one
thing I wanted to let you guys know
about is um Habitat for Humanity for the
month of March is uh currently uh at
Wagen Hound uh Winery in the uh Hines
building. And so, Jackson has been kind
enough for the month of March to um for
a party flight. 20% of the proceeds go
uh to Habitat towards the Blitz project
uh that's about to take place here, you
know, in the next couple of months. So,
if when he's open, if you guys could go
down there, get a party flight to assist
Habitat for Humanity. Also, in case I'm
sure most of you have probably got it in
your inboxes already, um Ashley may have
sent out um invites, you know, for the
Blitz build for election or, you know,
elected officials to, you know, come
speak, you know, or excuse me, not to
come speak, but to actually come work,
you know, and yeah, you guys talk
enough. Um I know so do I. Three
minutes. So yeah, if you guys could um
get with Ashley at Habitat, you know, to
make sure that uh you guys are in on it
to uh do the build and I don't know if
they have the schedule posted. Um then
some things that I've just been kind of
watching, Mark,
it's fun to say, you know, Microsoft and
Magpole and everybody uh you know, may
have some excess fees. Tell you're
looking a family in the face that's died
under a p or a under an emergency.
That's no fun. So, always watch, you
know, when you name big corporations,
when later down the line, uh, families
are in your face asking, you know, why
you happen, you're like, "Well,
Microsoft had a $5,000 bill, so I'm
sorry your your kid died." So, always be
careful. I'm That's just a little
political philosophy that I learned the
hard way because I always put my foot in
my mouth. Um, [snorts] another thing
that um comes up is I wanted to tell uh
when Michelle made the comment um two
weeks ago about one individual saying
that, you know, it wasn't unanimous that
everybody was against the farm. I was on
social media and I wrote that, you know,
I was in favor of the annexation, but
they kind of just blew it off, you know,
and then when she said that, you know,
the the chat went wild. But I want to,
you know, I have a I'm in a rare weird
place. Yes, I did lose an election, but
when my voice actually sends an email to
council, remember in 2024 I had over
3,000 supporters. You know that and my
supporters were, you know, some of them
were pretty straight laced, but for the
most part, they were like me. They
thanks to Gunnar, I look like Guy Fiery,
you know, tonight. So, [snorts] I'm sure
you guys will all see Gunner's meme if
he hasn't already texted you that today.
But no, but I just want you, you know,
you know, when bet.
>> What's that?
>> Did you lose a bet?
>> No, I'm just bored.
>> Okay.
>> Um, it'll be silver in two weeks. I'm
going to look like you. [laughter]
>> So, anyways, so I I just want to tell
you that it's it I listen to the
commentary that came through with um
with the Farm Fresh and stuff and and
when everybody's just like, "Nobody's
here to speak on this. Nobody's here to
speak on this." So, I always still do
like litmus tests through my, you know,
my co-workers just to see where
everybody's at in the community. And
guess what? They're like, I don't know
what you're talking about. You know,
they they don't follow this stuff. And
you have to remember that the only time
they really do is at an election. And
so, you know, you can always talk like
that all these people are, you know, you
know, out there. The silent majority if
you go back to like Nixon in the 70s or
or Moon Beam, um, sorry. So, when it
goes to that, but you always have to
remember that there's more people out
there that vote that may not think like
everybody that's screaming at the
microphone, and that includes me because
I don't know where I'm at half the time,
especially when I'm dying my hair. But I
did, you know, the really reason I
wanted to come up here is I was like,
don't forget that you represent the
entire community. you know, even if they
don't agree with you or maybe sometimes
they do, but really my um point under
other businesses, I really do hope you
guys will uh get with Ashley for Habitat
and start um you know, getting that set
up and so because it's going to be a lot
of fun. This is the biggest build that
they've ever done over there on on Story
Boulevard. So, yep. I hope I can count
on you guys to support and, you know,
help me like Jeff and Mark have in the
past doing you know, siding. So, it's
super fun. You learn a lot of on the job
tools. You meet a lot of really nice
people and this one's going to be one of
the biggest ones. If any of you know any
sponsors, you know, for like um you
know, coffee in the morning type stuff
like that, you know, reach out. So,
thank you guys once again for your time.
>> Thanks, Richard. Good to see you
tonight. Anybody else want to speak
under other business?
>> Anybody online?
>> Okay. How about from the governing body?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh Mayor Collins through you. I just
wanted to uh give a shout out to the
Cheyenne Animal Shelter. This last
Saturday, they held a uh vaccination
clinic at South High School. Um it
started at 10 am. They had people
starting to line up at 8 am. People
waited in line for three hours um to get
their pets vaccinated. They vaccinated
over 293 pets. Um and it was
underwritten by the uh Cheyenne Animal
Shelter Foundation. So, um, just wanted
to give a shout out to their staff and
to Doc Tess and the folks that worked on
that, um, immunization clinic. I think
that, uh, it shows that there's a huge
demand in our community for, um, people
that want to do right by their pets and
are looking for affordable ways to do
that through the these vaccine clinics.
Um and I would hope that um my
colleagues would uh support as will I'm
sure the community will the whiskered
event that will be held on uh in April
uh to benefit the Shy Animal Shelter
Foundation. So um just a shout out to
the folks that are working hard to keep
um the pets in our community safe as
well as the folks that own those pets.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Oh, thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you uh
thank you everybody for your public
comments. I just want to say for next
week, welcome Shiny Young back to our
community. You know, really great show.
I'm looking excited to see it. And also,
uh, happy Passover and a happy Easter
next week, too. Thank you.
>> Anybody else? Me,
>> Mr. Crave. Thank you, sir. I want to say
a huge shout out to all of our staff.
The last two weeks we've gone through
unbelievable
um issues [clears throat] with the wind
that has occurred. Um I want to say
thank you to everybody that's out there
cutting up trees, uh putting up uh
safety barriers. Uh I know our police
responded to three or four times the
number of calls as did our firefighters.
But it doesn't stop there. It goes to
the accounting department that that that
does the extra payroll. It it runs
through the entire organization and
honestly um the way everybody responded
is just amazing. It truly is and I just
want to say a great thank you to all of
you. I appreciate it very much.
>> I was looking at my note because u our
CRA director sent me a couple of things
that I wanted to talk about. Um on top
of all of that, we had uh the state
gymnastics championships. We had the
start of high school softball. We had a
couple shows at the civic center. I
mean, it was amazing um how those teams
and all of our teams pulled together um
to make sure the city was safe and uh
and that we got back to normal and the
kids got to do their their state
championships and uh and their
competitions and it's just uh um
something that makes us all proud. So,
thank you very much. Anybody else?
All right. With nothing else on our
agenda, we are adjourned. Uh we're going
to take about five minutes to uh
rearound our uh our tables here and then
we'll start uh some negotiations with
our fire union. So thank you all for
being here.
>> Recording stopped
recording in progress.
I would like to call the special meeting
of the governing body to order. Madame
clerk,
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> present.
>> Mayor Collins,
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> present.
>> Mr. Esabel.
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> present.
>> Mr. Moody,
>> here.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> present.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> Mr. White,
>> present.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> here.
>> One member is absent. Mayor, we do have
a quorum. Wonderful. Would you please
join me in the pledge of
>> allegiance
to the flag of the United States of
America and to the republic for it
stands one nation
indivisible with liberty and justice for
all.
Item number four, collective labor
bargaining with the Cheyenne
Professional Firefighters International
Association of Firefighters, local
number 279.
>> Thank you. I've got a quick statement I
want to make, but I want to change two
numbers.
Mr. Presidents, members, the eboard um
from the very beginning of this process,
I think our governing body's heard your
concerns that your concern of salaries
lagging behind the market by 30%. So,
we've took that observation seriously
and we've tried to understand and
frankly we can't get our math to support
30%.
Our staff
did a spreadsheet. We did every employee
with their full compensation without
overtime and we averaged each rank and
we compared that to the maximum salary
of the Wyoming departments. Um
you guys challenged some of those
inputs. So we tried again and we did
inputs that uh that would only show up
in a paycheck. So some of the clothing
allowances and things that did not make
sense for you guys, we took out of that
rate. And then we looked at the years in
rank and we compared the steps of our
average salary to the step a firefighter
in the other communities that would be
in a similar position. And um we use the
community council for economic research
which uh compares how expensive it is to
live in one city compared to another.
And it's based on actual prices of goods
and services. So they look at housing,
groceries, utilities, transportation,
healthcare, and they set the national
averages of 100. And uh it consists of a
it it's consistent basket of goods
updated quarterly to be able to compare
the cost of living um between
communities. And so we we did that and
we included uh Casper's recently
finished negotiations which ended up
with the firefighters and engineers
getting a 1% raise. their lieutenant or
their company officers, I think their
captains, aren't they in their
community? 2.75 and their battalion
chiefs getting a 3.25%
raise. And so we did the math again
comparing our firefighters and example
would be um our base firefighters are
just under four years average in
service. So we compared that to a
four-year average firefighter in other
communities. And when we compared that,
we were higher than every community at
every rank. And so I went back again and
I looked and said, "Well, what if we um
added in some of their acting pays,
things like that?" Um so when I looked
at Gillette, the maximum they can get is
$2,400 a year. And even when you add in
the maximum for every firefighter at
every rank, we still rank higher at
every rank. Sheridan, Laramie, um,
Leland, we're not quite there. We are,
um, we're 3.3% behind in firefighters,
7.9% behind in engineers, lieutenant, 7%
uh, behind. Um, but we also get $300,000
more in retirement, and we run 44% less
calls. Um, and then I looked at our
paramedic pay. Interesting. It's
$7,767.20
a year. So when I look at what a
paramedic is paid over their career,
let's say they become a paramedic in
their fifth year, it'd be 155,000. But
when you take that 70% of that that
number and you put it over a 30-year
career, it comes to $318,000 more a
paramedic makes in a career and in a
retirement. And we pay for the school
and we pay for all the costs to do that.
When I compare that to other
departments, like when I talked to the
chief from Rock Springs today, they do
have a paramedic pay, but they don't pay
for anything. The uh the firefighter has
to pay for the school, and their
reimbursement um or their their pay was
intended to reimburse the firefighter
for the cost. He said he thinks it cost
him about $24,000
to go to paramedic school. And then they
have to do shift trades, kind of like
what we have to do in order to be able
to get there. Um,
so
we we've tried to look at a number of
different ways to do a comparison, but
to uh maybe provide one last opportunity
to uh you know to come up with a a fair
offer to you guys. Um we have one more
thing we'd like to offer and that is a
3% raise for everyone. 3% on all your
added pays, longevity, EMT, shift
trainers, education, acting, all of our
special all of our add-on pays. And then
to address the recruit recruitment
concerns, we'll take the probationary
firefighter up to 10 10.4%. So they'll
be less four 5% less than a firefighter
step four. And then to address the um
the compression, we would increase the
the captain's pay by 3.5% in addition to
the 3% and the battalion chief's 4.75%
um to uh to help with some of those
compression issues because there's only
a couple percent difference in those
ranks. And so, um that would be an offer
that we would be willing to make. And I
apologize, we transcribed two of those
numbers backwards. I wrote him in there
in the correct form. You can hand that
to our clerk.
>> Thank you, Mayor Collins. Uh we'd like
to take a moment to caucus to review
this proposal.
>> Thank you.
The rest of the offer that we had was
the same as before.
Welcome back.
Thank you, Mayor Collins.
[clears throat]
The union would like to begin by
thanking the mayor and the members of
the city council for bringing forward
this proposal tonight. We also want to
acknowledge the city's willingness
to address the wage compression issues,
which is an important step towards
maintaining a fair and functional pay
structure within the department. In the
interest of making meaningful progress,
the union is prepared to move towards
resolution on wages with the following
framework.
The union is willing to accept the
city's proposed 3% increase with the
understanding that it is applied as a
market-based wage adjustment, not a cost
of living adjustment.
This distinction insurer ensures the
increase directly addresses market
competitiveness and retention concerns
contingencies and package agreement.
This package is this proposal is
contingent upon the following
extension of the cola sunset clause that
is currently in the collective labor
agreement. The existing sunset provision
for colas and other city for other city
employees shall be extended as proposed
for the duration of this collective
labor agreement.
>> I didn't quite understand that. Can you
explain that to me?
>> Can you pull up the
Do you have a copy of
>> Yeah. Do you have it? Okay.
>> Are you just saying that 3% that we did
January 1st becomes permanent? Is that
what you're saying?
>> No. No, that's not what I'm saying. That
that is structured in already. Um this
is building upon that. Okay.
What page?
>> Here we go. [snorts] Um, I believe it's
on page 34 of the current collective
agreement
section 21, classification of employment
and basic wages.
Let's see.
So, currently there's a sunset clause in
there. Um, in the event that the city of
Cheyenne employees receive a cost of
living adjustment during this contract
period, members, meaning members of the
union shall receive an equivalent
increase at the same time, expiring on
June 30th, 2026 at 11:59 p.m. We're
proposing that's extended for the
duration of the upcoming collective
labor agreement.
>> So, it would the sunset would be I
>> understand. Okay.
The second contingency that we have is
acceptance of the MERP language as
proposed.
We want to emphasize that the MERP is a
critically important item that supports
the long-term health and well-being of
our firefighters.
It is also a legacy item for this union
and we believe that this agreement
presents an opportunity for the city to
be a part of this lasting legacy.
This proposal reflects a good faith
effort to recognize the city's movement,
build on areas of agreement, and
continue working towards a fair and
sustainable contract for both parties.
Thank you,
Mr. President, members of the Eboard,
if we on the second page can agree on
the vacations,
I would be meanable to talk about the
MER. So, one of my biggest priorities in
this contract is to try to get overtime
under control.
I don't think anybody's doing overtime
to be malicious, but I just think we're
set up to fail in that.
And again, maybe I don't have a clear
understanding, but in October to
December, the uh vacation slots are
picked and then after that, EOD slots
are picked and as long as it doesn't
cause an overtime, we can go down to the
minimum staffing. Now, somebody gets
sick, somebody gets hurt, automatically
we're going to have an overtime. And so,
the language that we propose is four
vacation slots
>> [snorts]
>> um would be available for selection.
And then uh if application slots's not
filled, I believe we could use a EOD as
long as it doesn't create it two st two
slots above the minimum.
As I understand the math, we can fit all
of the vacation that we required or the
hours that we require for members of the
union in three days. We're not asking
for that. We're asking for four days.
>> And if we could agree to this language,
I would be open-minded to um to the mer
with one exception. And that was
language that chief of staff Ash talked
about and that is we like we have a
current firefighter that's on non-paid
uh not working without pay. We shouldn't
have to pay the the money when they're
not paying. So as long as the
firefighters paying into it, we would
pay into it. I think that language that
I think that's the only thing that we
had in um as an exception to to that.
So, if we could agree on the um uh the
vacation uh as is written, um I think I
can get around to a mer.
I have one amendment I'd like to make to
the vacation language, and that is uh
those four vacation slots. I want them
to be for vacation or EOD slots. That
gives our membership availability to to
use those slots and still be able to use
their comp time. Anything beyond that
would then fall into the criteria of the
two slots above minimum and not cause an
overtime at the time it's taken.
>> Give me two seconds to go talk to the
chief. I want to make sure I understand
how this works and I'll be right back.
>> Absolutely.
Okay. Let's see what your understanding
and my understanding are. Okay.
>> Sure. Sure.
>> So, we have four slots every day, 365
days. Uh from October 1st to December
1st, vacation slots are are taken. So,
every member is has exhausted all of
their vacation acrals.
>> Correct. Then if there's a day there's
three and somebody wants to take an EOD
day, they can take it up to so there's
up to four slots can be can be taken.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Um but we'll still be two slots above
the minimum when uh when the BC gets
there. So if there's an injury or
sickness or whatever, we'll we'll always
have two slots above the minimum.
>> Yes, that is my understanding as well.
>> Um I think that's what we're asking for.
>> Okay.
>> So I think we could agree to that. And
um also to for second part that um that
Amber presented. Yes, I'm I'm agreeable
to that as well.
>> Yes. Okay.
>> Yes.
And I'm not sure how we're going to let
the treasurer know that happens. So
we'll have to that'll be incumbent upon
us to somehow get that word to the
treasur that we don't do that.
We had sick leave um on our list uh
section 20 uh section 27 of the contract
um which would allow
um day personnel to take uh sick leave.
>> Yeah, we're we're agreeable with that.
>> I thought there was one more thing.
>> [snorts]
>> And then the last thing
[clears throat]
uh I think was number eight. We're we're
struggling when people leave in getting
a cruel setup. Um if someone quits um
it's in section 20 section 27.
Um,
we we have we have a number of things
there, but number eight is
if someone quits on the 10th of of the
month.
>> What we'd like to say is uh you have to
work a full month to gain an acural. So,
if you live on the 10th, you're not
going to get any acrals to longevity and
those things because it's very difficult
for us to to figure out calculate those
and pay them out and still meet the FSA
timelines. So, um,
and and that's how we do it with all of
our employees. So, we just want to make
that consistent with everybody else and
and help um Amber and and U
and I think it's Kelly in our uh HR
office. And number seven talks about uh
members affected by military deployments
or may be able to um schedule work um
uh vacation times
section 27 number seven
>> I believe it's actually I've got section
>> do I have it wrong there
>> section 26. I'm tracking where you met.
>> There's too many pages here and I'm
tired.
>> I I understand.
>> Yep. [snorts]
Six and seven were were mostly uh six
was in case there's an emergency. Uh it
gives flexibility for our uh
leadership to be able to grant somebody
some emergency leave. Uh an exception to
our our our policy. Um
I think there should be some room for
that.
we would be agreeable to all that. Um,
one thing we do want to to um add to
that under the vacation section is the
conversion of benefit hours um for our
daytime personnel. We use that
correction factor on literally
everything else of theirs and we'd like
to apply it um as we've proposed
uh to them to to make them whole. And I
hate to be a stick in the mud on this
one, but uh you know I've read what
eight or 10 different contracts. Every
one of them treats daytime and plutonium
differently. And I think for two
reasons. One is the flexibility that a
daytime person has. If you want to go
have lunch with your wife, you can do
that. You guys are on duty. You can't do
that. So there's a lack of flexibility.
And we have 11 or 12 paid holidays in
this city that they get to take
advantage of that you don't. So when
you're on holiday or you're working and
it's um New Year's Day, you have to
work. Those dates person don't have
those 11 days off. They're already
getting that extra time off.
>> So quite frankly, I I cannot agree to
that. And if you if you've read all
those contracts, the everyone has a
conversion for a day. So when you go
from from platoon to day, it goes down
and when you come back, it goes the
other way.
>> So honestly, I don't think that that's a
good policy. We we agreed to do it for
pay a couple years ago. Um, you guys
made a compelling argument. Lieutenant's
a lieutenant. We agreed to that. But the
one thing we pushed back on was the
vacation time because quite frankly, I
believe they have significant
flexibility and they're already getting
I can't remember if it's 11 or 12 paid
days off on top of what we're doing. So,
if you add those hours, they're already
there.
>> Okay. That's that's not the hill I'm
going to die on tonight. So,
>> okay. Um going back to um your earlier
statements regarding uh working the the
whole month to acrew that vacation and
leave. I'm agreeable to that.
>> Okay.
>> Was [snorts] was there one more again?
I'm sorry that you
>> exception 26. We had emergency
exceptions. Um
>> yes. Yes.
>> Yep. And so this gives the on duty
battalion chief, deputy chief or fire
chief. They can grant vacation time or
use of EOD um in that window that we're
not supposed to if it's an emergency.
and it's just they can't cause an
overtime. So, so if we have a um
humanitarian reason or for whatever that
would be, we would like to be able to uh
and we agree to that.
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
[snorts]
And then the part about vacations being
scheduled and used each calendar year,
>> correct? Okay. The number eight. Yes.
>> Okay. That's all agreeable.
>> Yes.
I think that's everything that was on
our list. Chief, did I forget anything?
>> Is there anything else on your list?
>> Uh, no.
We agreeable with with our proposal with
the the wages and the mer?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Okay. Uh, do you want me to get with uh
Chief Dyron tomorrow to finalize any
language? And
>> uh, Chief won't be here tomorrow. I
believe he's on spring break with his
family as is. Okay.
>> Deputy Chief Wood.
>> Okay.
>> So,
>> I can get with Chief.
>> He's running the show right now along
with the battalion chiefs. Um, but we'll
uh we'll probably next week we can get
all together and finalize all the
language and then um we'll bring that to
the governing body here in two weeks.
>> Okay. Um,
can we get that done in time, Lisa?
>> Okay.
>> Okay. All right.
>> All right. If there's nothing else, I
think we can adjourn.
>> All right. Thank you. Thank you all of
you for all of your time this month. I
appreciate it. [applause]
>> Thank you guys as well. Thank you.
Appreciate you as well.
>> Recording stopped.